We start today at the bottom of עמוד א', Amud Aleph, we
will try to cover דף ו' Daf Vav today, but we start
at the very bottom of עמוד א', Amud Aleph, very last line,
תיופתא דרבנן תיופתא, Tiyuvta de-Rabbanan Tiyuvta, where we have the ברייתא Baraita
that says that a מומר Mumar can be שוחט, Shochet, and we
have two explanations for it. One explanation is a מומר אוכל נבילות
לתיאבון, Mumar Ochel Nevelot Le-Te'avon, somebody who basically doesn't care about כשרות,
Kashrut, and the other explanation is a real מומר, Mumar, somebody who
even is an idolater. And which of the... and the גמרא Gemara
finally rejected that second explanation based on a ברייתא Baraita that also
put in the same category somebody who is a public violator of
שבת. Shabbat. So this is the classic sort of approach that we
are familiar with, that an idolater and a violator of שבת Shabbat
is categorically excluded from a range of מצוות Mitzvot and is seen
as like a real invalidity of the person's status. And in the
end, we're left with the explanation that if somebody just violates a
single thing, even if it's כשרות, Kashrut, they still could be trusted
to do the שחיטה Shechita correctly under the right circumstances. So that
is where we are right now where what we have not excluded
the אוכל נבילות לתיאבון, Ochel Nevelot Le-Te'avon, we have excluded the idolater
and the public violator of שבת, Shabbat, and that is certainly where
our tradition, where the הלכה Halacha is for us. So now we
pick up on the very last line. The גמרא Gemara says the
following: והא מהכא נפקא מהתם נפקא? Ve-ha me-hakha naffka me-hatam naffka? Do
we really learn it from there, from this פסוק Pasuk about מכם
Mi-kem to exclude a מומר Mumar from bringing sacrifices? We really learn
it from another פסוק Pasuk that a מומר Mumar is excluded from
bringing sacrifices. Where is that? מעם הארץ, Me-am ha-aretz, it says that
if somebody brings a sin offering from the people of the land,
and the מ' Mem means from,
not all. פרט למומר, Prat le-mumar, it excludes somebody that is a
violator or a rebel, that that person does not bring a sin
offering. רבי שמעון יוסי אומר, Rabbi Shimon Yosei omer, רבי שמעון יוסי
Rabbi Shimon Yosei says משום רבי שמעון, mishum Rabbi Shimon, in the
name of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, אשר לא תעשינה בשגגה ואשם. Asher
lo te-asena bi-shgaga ve-ashem. The פסוק Pasuk says that a person does
a sin that you would not normally do and you did it
in error and he is guilty. So from here we learn out:
השב מדעתו מביא קרבן על שגגתו, Ha-shav mi-da'ato mevi korban al shigagato,
that somebody that, were he to not have been a שוגג, shogeg,
were he to be aware of what he was doing incorrectly, would
bring a קרבן korban as a result of his error. But אינו
שב מדעתו, eino shav mi-da'ato, somebody who would not normally,
somebody who would not change his ways if he was aware that
he was doing something wrong, so that person אינו מביא קרבן על
שגגתו, eino mevi korban al shigagato, does not bring a קרבן korban
for his error. Meaning, if you would have done it, you might
have sinned in error, but if you would have sinned anyway even
had you not been in error, even had
you
known the facts, even had
you been prepared to sin intentionally, so that type of a person
does not bring a קרבן. korban. I'm a person that I eat
טריפה. tereifa. This time I thought I was eating kosher and it
happened to be טריפה. treif. So I'm not going to bring a
קרבן korban because even if I knew it was טריפה treif I
would have eaten it. That's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. So
these are two people that are excluded from being קרבן, korban, somebody
that's a מומר, mumar, somebody that sins, regularly sins, and somebody that
would have done it anyway. So the גמרא Gemara asks, what's the
difference? Let's take a look. ואמרינן Ve-amrinan and we said, מאי בינייהו?
mai beinaihu? What's the difference? Both of them are saying that if
a person is a regular sinner you don't bring a קרבן. korban.
ואמר רב המנונא, Ve-amar Rav Hamnuna, מומר לאכול חלב והביא קרבן על
הדם איכא בינייהו. Mumar le-ekhol chelev ve-hevi korban al hadam ika beinaihu.
No, the difference is somebody that normally sins in one type of
area but he accidentally now sinned in a different area. This person
is a regular eater of forbidden fat. That's the only thing he
violates. Other things he doesn't violate. This time it happened that he
accidentally ate blood, okay? Which is another forbidden food, and as תוספות
Tosafot point out, it's a very linked forbidden food because the Torah
prohibits fat and blood in the same way because they're both things
that are normally given from the sacrifices, they're both punishable by כרת.
Karet. So it's in the same sort of universe of forbidden foods,
but it's different. Okay? But normally this person doesn't eat blood. He
only eats fat. This time he ate blood by accident. So what's
the story? So does he bring a קרבן? korban?
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't spell it out, but the difference is
the following: if you say that the only reason you don't bring
a קרבן korban is because you would have done it anyway, then
this guy says I wouldn't have done it anyway. If it were
fat, I would have done it anyway, but for blood, that I
wouldn't have done. Oh, so since you wouldn't have done it anyway,
then you bring a קרבן korban because normally you wouldn't have done
it and you only did it by an error. But if the
issue is you don't bring a קרבן korban because you are a
מומר, mumar, because your status is a person that's a regular sinner,
so since you're a regular sinner of fat, even though you're not
a regular sinner of blood, since you are this habitual regular sinner,
you're not going to bring a קרבן korban regardless. Now... תוספות Tosfos
points out that it's only because you're a habitual sinner in a
linked related area. Remember yesterday we said that just because a person,
if we're not dealing with something like שבת Shabbos or עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, just because a person is a sinner for like eating
non-kosher food, does not generally invalidate them. So here we're not saying
that just because this person is a habitual sinner about חלב, Cheilev,
they're generally invalidated. What they are, though, is that they're excluded from
bringing sin offerings in this cluster of sins, cluster of behavior. So
included in the cluster of behavior of חלב Cheilev is also the
eating of דם, Dam, even though you normally don't eat דם, Dam,
but it's part of the same, what I would say פרשה, Parsha,
and therefore you're completely excluded from bringing a sin offering in that.
So anyway, what do we have? We have before we excluded from
a sin offering a person that is a idolater and a שבת
Shabbos violator, that type of a thing is called a מומר Mumar
and is categorically excluded. And now we've excluded from bringing a קרבן
Korban somebody that either would have sinned anyway, or somebody that would
have been at least, you know, been a habitual violator in this
area of behavior, even if not in this particular thing. Okay? And
that is, so now the גמרא Gemara says, why do I have
to exclude a מומר Mumar in two cases? Now of course part
of the answer is that we're excluding different types of מומר, Mumar,
but the גמרא's Gemara bracketing that and says why do I need
two different ways, two different types of ways of excluding a מומר?
Mumar? You had a question.
Are these people formally defined as מומרים Mumarim if they are they
publicly addressed?
I mean, I have no idea, that's a good question.
There's no legal in that definition. I don't think they'd go around
like with a sign on their forehead or something like that.
No, I don't think it was anything like that. Not that I
know of, not that I know of.
In other words, rumored has it that?
Right, yeah. How would that status be established and so on? I
mean, there is some discussion in הלכה Halacha about like whether there
needs to be, it has to be in front of a, like
there has to have been testimony about this, does a בית דין
Beis Din have to be aware, how much like for the שבת
Shabbos violator in public, how do you define public? But I don't
think it meant that the person went around town with like a
big mark on his forehead or something like that. No, no, that
we know, we never hear of. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
wants to know why do we have to exclude a מומר Mumar
twice from bringing a קרבן? Korban? So the גמרא Gemara says, חד
בחטאת וחד בעולה וצריכי. Chad Be'Chatas Ve'Chad Be'Olah U'Tzrichi. No, because one
excluded a person from a חטאת Chatas and one excluded him from
an עולה, Olah, and you need both cases. דאי אשמעינן חטאת, De'Ee
Ashmieinan Chatas, had it just said a חטאת, Chatas, משום דכפרה היא,
Mishum De'Chapparah Hi, that that is for atonement.
So maybe you don't deserve atonement if you are such a willful
violator. So you're not deserving of atonement. אבל עולה, Aval Olah, but
if it was an עולה, Olah, דדורון הוא, De'Doron Hu, that's a
gift to God. So, you know, that's not such an affront to
bring a gift even though you're a violator, אימא לקבל מיניה, Eima
Lekabbel Minei, maybe it should be accepted. ואי אשמעינן עולה, Ve'Ee Ashmieinan
Olah, had it just said we don't accept an עולה Olah from
a מומר, Mumar, from a habitual violator, משום דלאו חובה הוא, Mishum
De'Lav Chovah Hu, he has no obligation, so therefore we say, you
know, he's going to be excluded from an עולה Olah because he's
not entitled to bring it, he's a habitual violator and he has
no obligation to bring it. אבל חטאת, Aval Chatas, but a sin
offering, דחובה הוא, De'Chovah Hu, that there's an obligation to bring a
sin offering, אימא לקבל מיניה, Eima Lekabbel Minei, maybe that we should
bring it from him, maybe that it's more insistent that it should
be brought and we're not so ready to exclude him. Also, as
רש"י Rashi says, we don't want him to benefit, just because he's
a sinner he gets out of an obligation. צריכא. Tzricha. So it
tells me both cases. Now again, as, you know, תוספות Tosfos points
out, they're not really the same. In one case I exclude somebody
that's a מומר Mumar because he's really categorically excluded, he's an idolater
or he's a שבת Shabbos violator. In the other case I'm excluding
a מומר Mumar because it's not appropriate to bring a sin offering
if you're a willful violator, or even if you're not a willful
violator of this itself, if you're a willful violator of a related
area of behavior. Okay, but anyway those are the two ways in
which we exclude מומר Mumar from a קרבן. Korban. Back to our
issue, more relevant for us is is that the type of a
person that is categorically excluded in general is the idolater and the
שבת Shabbos violator, but if you sin in a particular area, even
if it's the same area, even if it's כשרות, Kashrus, given the
right circumstances we might trust you to be a שוחט. Shochet. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues and it sort of focuses now
on a side point about the ברייתא Beraisa we quoted before. It
says וכל היכא דכתיב בהמה גרועה היא. Ve'Chol Heicha De'Kesiv Beheimah Geruah
Hi. If you remember the ברייתא Beraisa before said that since the
verse said בהמה, Beheimah, that it taught
that even people that are sinners like animals, they're as bad as
animals, even those people can bring קרבנות. Korbanos. So it says, does
the word בהמה Beheimah really mean like an insult? People that are
like as bad as animals? והכתיב, Ve'Hakesiv, I'll give you a place
where it says something positive, אדם ובהמה תושיע ה', Adam U'Beheimah Toshiya
Hashem,
man and beast God will save. So it's something good that they're
saved, it's not really used here as an insult, so or as
a derogatory term. And how do I know it? Because here's how
we explain it. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Ve'Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Rav, אלו בני אדם שהן ערומים בדעת, Eilu Bnei Adam Shehen Arumim
Be'Daas, this refers, this בהמה Beheimah that God saves, to people that
are Sly in their intellect, ומשימין עצמם כבהמה, umesimin atzmam kebeheimah,
and treat themselves like a בהמה, beheimah, meaning that they are very
humble and lowly and they're not arrogant. These are the people that
God will save. So here בהמה beheimah is used as a positive
connotation, that it means you are humble, and so how come we
before assume that the word בהמה beheimah means a what do you
call it, means somebody that is means a sinner? So the גמרא
Gemara says, התם כתיב אדם ובהמה, hasam ksiv adam uveheimah, הכא בהמה
לחודיה כתיב. hacha beheimah lechudei ksiv.
No,
there it says man and beast, so beast is connected to man,
so we're going to interpret it in a positive way, a type
of a human being that is humble like an
animal, does not non-arrogant. When it just says בהמה beheimah by itself,
then we're going to interpret it in a negative way as a
sinner. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכל היכא דכתיב אדם ובהמה מעליותא
היא? vechol heicha dechsiv adam uveheimah malyusa hi? So now it's going
to not let up. It says, oh, but now you're telling me
that where it says man and beast it's a positive? והכתיב, vehachsiv,
I'll give you another example where it's a negative. וזרעתי את בית
ישראל זרע אדם וזרע בהמה. vezarati es beis yisrael zera adam vezera
beheimah.
I will plant the house of Israel, the planting of man, the
planting of animal. So what does this mean? I mean it's referring
to that we're going to be spread out in the גלות, galus,
but ultimately it's a positive that we'll sprout forth and so on
like the planting of a seed. And how do we know that's
a negative? Because the גמרא Gemara interprets this in סוטה Sotah to
say that this refers to people that are not learned in תורה.
Torah. So
and God is saying whether you are whether they're scholars or whether
they're ignoramuses I'm going to spread them out and plant them and
eventually they'll sprout forth and they'll multiply. So there at least we
interpret the word בהמה beheimah in a negative to mean ignoramuses, non-scholars.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, החלקי קרא, hachalki kra, זרע אדם
לחודיה וזרע בהמה לחודיה. zera adam lechudei vezera beheimah lechudei.
There it's not linking אדם adam and בהמה. beheimah. The earlier verse
said אדם ובהמה, adam uveheimah, so it really linked them. Here it
separates them, the planting of man, the planting of beast, so therefore
separate, so we're going to interpret the word beast in a negative
way. Okay, so anyway that's just wrapping up the fact that we
interpreted beast to mean sinners, sometimes we interpret negative, sometimes we interpret
positive. Now we get back to our main theme. So remember what
has been our main theme? Our main theme now has been focusing
on the types of people that are not acceptable to be שוחטים,
shochtim, or not not acceptable, questionably acceptable. One was the מומר, mumar,
the regular violator of eating non-שחיטה shechitah meat. And there רבא Rava
says and that presumably is how we remain, that if you give
him a checked knife and there's really no incentive for him to
do it wrong, we can assume he'll do it right even if
he's not observed, which is a pretty surprising thing. And now the
other person that we had been talking about was the כותי. Kuti.
And we had explored that also, the Samaritan, how much do you
assume that they do keep the laws, they don't keep the laws,
they keep them with scrupulousness, how do you make sure that they're
not trying to trip us up even if they keep it personally?
But the general פשט pshat was also there as well that under
the right circumstances a כותי Kuti you can trust their שחיטה. shechitah.
Okay, now we are going to revisit the case of כותי. Kuti.
So let's take a look. אמר רבי חנן אמר רבי יעקב אמר
רבי יעקב בר אידי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא
רבן גמליאל ובית דינו נמנו על שחיטת כותי ואסרוה. Amar Rabbi Chanan
amar Rabbi Yaakov amar Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi mishum Bar Kappara Rabban Gamliel uveiz dino nimnu al shechitas kuti
ve’asruha. Rabban Gamliel and his court took a vote, reassessed the
situation of the כותים, Kutim, and they made the שחיטה shechitah forbidden.
We don't know why yet, but although before we said it is
okay, here we are now saying that they made a decision to
say the שחיטה shechitah of a כותי Kuti is no good. אמר
ליה רבי זירא לרבי יעקב בר אידי. Amar lei Rabbi Zeira leRabbi
Yaakov bar Idi. So רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said to רבי יעקב
בר אידי, Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi, שמא לא שמע רבי אלא בשאין
ישראל עומד על גביו? shema lo shama Rebbe ella beshein yisrael omed
al gabav? Maybe when
maybe that this report here was only, because this was רבי יעקב
בר אידי Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi was the one who was reporting
it, so he said are you sure that's what they said? Are
you sure they said that we can't trust a כותי? Kuti? Maybe
it only means when there's no direct observation, when you're not עומד
על גביו? omed al gabav? Because that we know, that you need
to be directly observing a כותי, Kuti, either directly observing him or
making him eat from his own meat. If he'll eat from his
own meat, then you can trust it. But those were the two
circumstances. So he says maybe you don't mean we completely invalidate it.
Maybe you only mean we invalidate it if you haven't observed him
שחט-ing shecht it. Is it possible that's what you really were talking
about, that's what you really heard? אמר ליה. Amar lei. So he
said back to him, אמר ליה דמי האי מרבנן כדלא גמיר אינש
שמעתא. amar lei dami hai merabbanan kedlo gmir inash shma’ata. He says
it seems to me that this rabbi, meaning you who asked that
question, it's like you never learned anything in your life. What type
of stupid question is that? בשאין ישראל עומד על גביו למימרא בעי?
beshein yisrael omed al gabav l’meimra ba’ei? If he was not being
observed, would it have required a statement at all? Meaning we've always
taken for granted that a כותי Kuti is only good either if
it's under direct observation or if you make him eat from the
meat itself. So if I am coming and telling you that there
was a teaching going all the way back that רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel and his בית דין beis din said a כותי Kuti is
not good, I am obviously not talking that there obviously if there
was no direct observation it would be... purposeless to say it. We
all know that you need direct observation. So if I am telling
you a כותי Kuti is no good, it means even with direct
observation they've decided to not allow the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי.
Kuti. Now that really raises a serious question because if it's with
direct observation, so what could go wrong? You're directly looking at it,
right? Even a חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh Shoteh Vekatan with direct observation
is okay. So what could be wrong with the שחיטה Shechita of
a כותי Kuti if you are directly observing? And the only real
possibility is we only know of one category of people that even
with direct observation it's no good. And who is that? That is
the, that is a non-Jew because a non-Jew even if it's technically
done 100% correctly, is categorically excluded and the שחיטה Shechita of a
non-Jew is invalid, it needs to be שחט shechted by a Jew.
So here if they're saying that the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי
Kuti is not good even with direct observation, what it implicitly is
saying is they are categorizing כותים Kutim as non-Jews. And that is
what we are going to get to. Okay, so he says, but
then immediate response is what a stupid question that was, of course
it's direct observation, otherwise you wouldn't need to say anything.
So, קבלו מיניה או לא קבלו מיניה? Kiblu Minei O Lo Kiblu
Minei? Did he accept that response or not? Was he willing to
accept the idea that the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי Kuti is
not good even with direct observation? So, תא שמע, Ta Shma, come
and hear, דאמר רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר רב אסי, De'amar Rav
Nachman Bar Yitzchak Amar Rav Assi, אני ראיתי את רבי יוחנן, Ani
Ra'isi Es Rabi Yochanan, I saw רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan שאכל משחיטת
כותי, She'achal Mishchitas Kuti, I saw רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
who was prepared to eat from the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי.
Kuti. This is even after, obviously after רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and
בית דין Beis Din and after this teaching that we just had.
So where are we? שאכל משחיטת כותי. She'achal Mishchitas Kuti. ואף רב
אסי אכל משחיטת כותי, Ve'af Rav Assi Achal Mishchitas Kuti,
and even רב אסי Rav Assi was willing to eat from the
שחיטה Shechita of a כותי. Kuti. ותוה בה רבי זירא, Vesoh Bei
Rabbi Zeira, and רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira was astounded that they were
doing this after what we had just taught above. And he says,
and he wanted to know, and he was wondering the following. Either
he said, לא שמיע להו, Lo Shemia Lehu, they didn't hear this
report that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and his בית דין Beis Din
invalidated the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי, Kuti, דאי הוו שמיע להו
הוו מקבלי להו, De'ee Havu Shemia Lehu Havu Mekabli Lehu, had they
heard this report
they obviously would've accepted and they wouldn't be eating from the slaughtering
of a כותי. Kuti. That's one possibility, that they never heard this
report of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and his בית דין. Beis Din.
או דילמא, O Dilma, or רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said there's another
possibility, שמיע להו ולא קבלה. Shemia Lehu Velo Kibla.
Maybe they heard of the report and they didn't accept it. Okay,
so he didn't know. Here you had later אמוראים Amoraim eating from
the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי, Kuti, and רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
was saying what happened? We taught that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said
it's forbidden. Either they didn't hear that report, or they heard it
and they didn't accept it. Okay, now but the גמרא Gemara says
from here we can infer though how רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira is
interpreting this ruling that the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי Kuti is
not good. How? So the גמרא Gemara says like this, היכי, Heichi,
one minute. So the
גמרא Gemara
says או דילמא שמיע להו ולא קבלו. O Dilma Shemia Lehu Velo
Kiblu. הדר פשטה לנפשיה. Hadar Pashtah Lenafshei. Well first let's just finish
this point. And then he concluded for himself that it must be,
מסתברא, Mistavra, it makes sense, דשמיע להו ולא קבלו, Deshemia Lehu Velo
Kiblu, they must've heard the report but they didn't accept it. Why?
דאי סלקא דעתך לא שמיע להו, De'ee Salka Da'atach Lo Shemia Lehu,
if we were to think that they did not hear the report,
that they actually never got the message that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
and his בית דין Beis Din forbade it, ואי הוו שמיע להו
הוו מקבלי להו, Ve'ee Havu Shemia Lehu Havu Mekabli Lehu, and had
they heard it they would've accepted and wouldn't have eaten the meat,
היכי מסתייעא מילתא למיכל איסורא, Heichi Mistayei Miltha Lemachal Issura, how could
it ever have happened that God could've allowed it that these people
would've eaten forbidden food? Meaning, if they basically said 'yes, I know
that there's a story, that there's a report that רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel said the שחיטה Shechita is not good. But I don't פסק
pasken that way, I think the שחיטה Shechita is still kosher.' Okay,
you're entitled to פסק, pasken, it's kosher if somebody פסק paskens it's
not kosher, and therefore you're eating the meat. That scenario makes sense.
But if, were they to have heard that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
made it forbidden, they would've accepted it and they would've treated the
meat as not kosher, and the only reason they're eating the meat
now is because they didn't get the report, they didn't get the
memo, if that's true, how could God have allowed them to eat
meat that they themselves would've considered טרייף, traif, that is trayf meat?
Why not? השתא בהמתן של צדיקים אין הקדוש ברוך הוא מביא תקלה
על ידם, Hashta Behematan Shel Tzaddikim Ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu Mavi Takala
Al Yadam, if God doesn't even allow the animals of צדיקים Tzaddikim
to stumble, צדיקים עצמם לא כל שכן, Tzaddikim Atzmam Lo Kol Sheken,
how much more so God does not allow צדיקים Tzaddikim to stumble.
What's the idea of animals of צדיקים Tzaddikim to stumble? That there's
a story with the donkey of פנחס בן יאיר, Phineas Ben Yair,
which we're going to get to, that he would not eat, you
know, anything that he wasn't allowed to eat. Even a donkey wouldn't.
So if the donkeys of צדיקים Tzaddikim wouldn't eat it, how much
more so would God prevent צדיקים Tzaddikim themselves from eating non-kosher food.
So if they ate it, it must be that they פסק pasken
it was מותר. mutar. They ruled against this story, you know, this
statement that they forbade the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי Kuti and
they held that it was really okay. So now what we've seen
now is that there is a position that the שחיטה Shechita of
a כותי Kuti is not good even you know even with direct
observation, but and that's from all the way back to רבן גמליאל,
Rabban Gamliel, but nevertheless even later אמוראים Amoraim not everybody accepts it
and some people would eat from the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי
Kuti even in the even in the. you know even generations after
and disagreed with that ruling and said that it remained okay as
long as let's say there was direct observation. Now top of ו
עמוד א vav amud alef though, getting back to our question: did
Rabbi Zeira—how did Rabbi Zeira interpret the ruling of Rabban Gamliel? Did
he interpret it with or without a ישראל Yisrael observing it? So
now the גמרא Gemara says the following: ואי סלקא דעתך לא קיבלה
מיניה, ve'ee salka daitach lo kibla minei, if Rabbi Zeira did not
accept the response that Rabban Gamliel is talking about direct observation and
he wanted to explain that Rabban Gamliel is only talking about when
it wasn't observed, so why did he have a whole conniption here
about you know Rabbi Assi and Rabbi Yochanan eating from the שחיטה
shchita of a כותי? kooty? Maybe Rabban Gamliel when they said you
can't trust the שחיטה shchita of a כותי kooty was only when
it was not being directly observed. Okay, לישני ליה, lishni lei, why
couldn't he say כאן כשישראל עומד על גביו כאן כשאין ישראל עומד
על גביו kan kshe'yisrael omed al gabav kan kshe'ein yisrael omed al
gabav that the only time we excluded it was when it was
not being directly observed, but if it was being directly observed then
it would be okay? So remember Rabban Gamliel had this—there was a
statement Rabban Gamliel said שחיטה shchita of a כותי kooty not good.
And Rabbi Zeira wanted to say maybe that only means without—when it
wasn't observed. But if that—if he really held to that he wouldn't
have had a problem why these other אמוראים Amora'im ate from the
שחיטה shchita of a כותי kooty because he could have just said
oh I understand why they ate from it because that was when
it was being directly observed. Since he did not have that simple
solution, obviously in the end he accepted the fact that this statement
of Rabban Gamliel that the שחיטה shchita of a כותי kooty is
not good means in all circumstances, even when it's directly observed. אלא
לאו שמע מינה, ela lav shma mina, we hear from this is
קיבלה מיניה kibla minei did accept it שמע מינה shma mina we
hear that. Okay good, so now we are at a position where
there's a clear ruling that the שחיטה shchita of a כותי kooty
is not good even with direct observation. We don't know why yet
but we know that—I hinted to you what it's about—but that's what
we said. And the other position, which we have yet to say
is—the other position, even many generations after, rejects that and says that
the שחיטה shchita of a כותי kooty is still going to be—is
still going to be good. That was Rabbi Yochanan and Rabbi Assi
and so on. I want to say one thing, we're going to
get back to this, but about this line that—because we're going to
see it also later in today's דף—that daf God doesn't allow the
צדיקים tzaddikim you know to err. So there's a תוספות Tosafot here
says what do you talk about and he brings cases in the
גמרא Gemara where צדיקים tzaddikim sin you know and—because by mistake, like
they—they didn't realize whatever it was. So תוספות Tosafot says no, we're
talking very specifically about eating forbidden food. And whenever the גמרא Gemara
says בהמתן של צדיקים צדיקים עצמם לא כל שכן behemtan shel tzaddikim
tzaddikim atzmam lo kol sheken uses this story of פנחס בן יאיר
Pinchas ben Yair asks how could this צדיק tzaddik have sinned, God
wouldn't have allowed it, it specifically is talking about forbidden food. And
it seems to be because of this idea that then we're not
just talking about sin, then we're talking about something forbidden going into
your body and that is seen to be more problematic than just
the sin itself, but somehow has some corrupting effect you know physical
or even more so spiritual on your body. Now that's important because
that leads to a whole approach in הלכה halacha about how much
do we treat forbidden food as just any sin or do we
treat it as some objective wrong even if it's not about sin.
And one for example example is how about feeding infants or feeding
infants non-kosher food or at least allowing them to eat non-kosher food.
So if they're doing other things you don't stop your baby from,
I don't know, turning on the lights on שבת Shabbat right if
he's an infant not the age of חינוך. chinuch. Is food different?
Is somehow טריף treif food seen as having this corrupting effect that
goes beyond just the prohibition? So that's an interesting area that gets
discussed but that's obviously what's being echoed here that they can't imagine
that a צדיק tzaddik would eat non-kosher food even though sometimes a
צדיק tzaddik does do other types of things you know sins by
error. So that's that.